<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in Trinity-College Chappell before the University of Dublin, January the 9th, 1693/4 being the first Secular Day since its foundation by Queen Elizabeth / by St. George Ashe ...</title>
            <author>Ashe, St. George, 1658?-1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35285</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15194550</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15194550</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103235</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25995)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1139:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in Trinity-College Chappell before the University of Dublin, January the 9th, 1693/4 being the first Secular Day since its foundation by Queen Elizabeth / by St. George Ashe ...</title>
                  <author>Ashe, St. George, 1658?-1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Ray for William Norman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Dublin?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by the Lords Justices command."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXVI, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103235:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN Trinity-College Chappell, BEFORE THE UNIVERSITY OF DUBLIN <hi>JAN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARY</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> 1693/4.</p>
            <p>Being the Firſt SECULAR DAY SINCE ITS FOUNDATION BY Queen ELIZABETH.</p>
            <p>By <hi>St. George Aſhe,</hi> D. D. Provoſt of <hi>Trinity College, Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by the Lords Iuſtices Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Joſeph Ray</hi> on <hi>College Green,</hi> for <hi>William Norman</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Dames-ſtreet, Dublin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103235:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE HENRY, Lord CAPELL, Sir CYRILL WICH, and WILL: DUNCOMBE<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Eſq; LORDS JUSTICES OF IRELAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Obedience to Your Commands, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to Your Lordſhips the Diſcourſe I made before the <hi>Univerſity</hi> on our <hi>Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration-day,</hi> which I juſtly fear may fall much ſhort of that <hi>Favourable</hi> Character Your Lordſhips received of it from ſome very <hi>partial</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:103235:3"/> Auditors; I am ſenſible, (my Lords) that its <hi>ſtyle</hi> may appear too <hi>exalted</hi> and <hi>declamatory,</hi> and many <hi>Expreſſions</hi> more <hi>fanciful</hi> then may be thought by ſome agreeable to the Gravity of my Place, or my uſual way of Preaching; but that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I hope will be excuſed, in conſideration of the <hi>extraordinary Occaſion</hi> and <hi>Solemnity,</hi> and the numerous <hi>mixt Audience</hi> to whom it was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed.</p>
            <p>If it may any way contribute to Encourage the <hi>Study</hi> and <hi>Improvement</hi> of <hi>Learning,</hi> or Raiſe up any <hi>New Friends</hi> and <hi>Benefactors</hi> to our <hi>College,</hi> I ſhall think its Publication <hi>ſeaſonable:</hi> at leaſt, <hi>my Lords,</hi> let not any Miſtakes or Weakneſs in it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice Your Lordſhips againſt our Society, which You have hitherto ſo <hi>generouſly</hi> and <hi>kindly Protected.</hi> The <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Muſes</hi> are proud to call <hi>You</hi> their <hi>own,</hi> they glory in having formed <hi>Your Minds</hi> to that <hi>rare pitch</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> which is admired by all; and therefore 'tis from Your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> they chiefly expect <hi>Patronage</hi> and <hi>Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> from Your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> I ſay, whoſe more <hi>liberal Education, innate greatneſs</hi> of <hi>Mind,</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted Station</hi> in the World, give you a <hi>privilege</hi> to Reaſon <hi>above</hi> the <hi>common rate</hi> of <hi>Mankind,</hi> and to <hi>Protect</hi> all ſuch as endeavour to do ſo, by Your <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Example.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:103235:3"/>
            <p> That Your <hi>Lordſhips zealous Endeavours</hi> for the <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Proſperity</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> may ever <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper,</hi> and Your <hi>Government</hi> long continue a bleſſing to us that live under its <hi>happy influence,</hi> ſhall be the conſtant Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Humble, and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>St. George Ashe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:103235:4"/>
            <head>THE PRAYER BEFORE SERMON.</head>
            <p>LET thy merciful Ears, O Lord, be open to the Prayers of thy Humble Servants, and grant that thy <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and guide us in all our ways, and be more eſpecially aſſiſtant to us in the Holy Actions of this day, in enabling us with <hi>grateful Hearts</hi> and <hi>zealous Endeavors</hi> to celebrate this Pious <hi>Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration,</hi> and to anſwer by our Studies and Improvements all the great and uſeful ends of our <hi>Munificent Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Benefactors.</hi> We render thee humble Praiſe and Thanks, O Lord, for the Moſt Serene Princeſs Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> our <hi>Illuſtrious Foundreſs;</hi> for King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> our moſt <hi>Liberal Benefactor;</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Second,</hi> our <hi>Gratious</hi> and <hi>Munificent Conſervators;</hi> for the protection and bounty we have received from their preſent <hi>Majeſties,</hi> our moſt <hi>Indulgent Patrons</hi> and <hi>Reſtorers;</hi> for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of our preſent Governours, the <hi>Right Honorable</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:103235:4"/> the <hi>Lords Juſtices;</hi> for the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this <hi>City,</hi> our Generous Benefactors; for the <hi>Nobility, Clergy,</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> of this Kingdom; thró whoſe Bounty and Charitable Generoſity we are here Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Eſtabliſhed; for the Improvement of Piety and Religion, the advancement of Learning, and to ſupply the growing neceſſities of Church and State; beſeeching thee to bleſs them all, their Poſterity, Succeſſors, Relations, and Dependants, with both <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Eternal</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and to give us Grace to live <hi>worthy</hi> of theſe thy Mercies, and that as we <hi>grow</hi> in <hi>Years</hi> ſo we may <hi>grow</hi> in <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Knowledg,</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> and all that is praiſeworthy thrô <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Lord</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:103235:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103235:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the UNIVERSITY of <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>St. Matthew XXVI. 13.</bibl>
               <q>Verily I ſay unto you, whereſoever this Goſpel shall be preached in the whole world, there shall alſo this, that this Woman has done, be told for a memorial of her.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F ſuch univerſal Obligation is the great duty of Gratitude, ſo neceſſary an ingredient is it both to a Holy and a Happy Life; that our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour who came into the World to teach us Virtue in every inſtance, could not be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to inculcate as well by Example as Precept this general parent one, this Original Spring which gives force and activity to ſo many leſſer Graces, which makes Love to admire, Joy to applaud, Humility to reflect upon the indigence of humane Nature that needed ſuch benefits, Thankfulneſs ever to celebrate 'em, and ſets 'em all inceſſantly at work to perform its various Offices. A certain Pious Woman (as we read in the Verſes preceding, the ſame who in another Goſpel <hi>choſe the better part, the one thing needful)</hi> having profited much by the Doctrine of Jeſus, and been witneſs to many of his Miracles, to expreſs her ſence thereof, brought the moſt pretious thing ſhe had, <hi>a Box of coſtly Ointment, and pour'd it on his Head as he ſat at Meat,</hi> ſo that it ran down to all the parts of his body, and with its grateful odour fill'd the whole houſe; this kind
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103235:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> act of hers our Saviour in my Text thus ſolemnly and grateful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledges, and declares that it ſhall be for ever celebrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and remembred.</p>
            <p>Now how parallel this caſe is to the occaſion of our preſent Meeting, a little reflexion may evince: A Princeſs the moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent for Piety, Learning, Chaſtity, and Happy Government that ever bleſſed theſe Kingdoms, having enlightened our n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ighbouring Nation with the brightneſs of the Reformation, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d fenc'd it in by Laws and juſt Authority againſt all the open force and ſecret contrivances of Popery or Schiſm; took into Her Royal Thoughts alſo the care and concerns of our poor Iſland, almoſt quite over-run with Barbarity and Superſtition, and as the moſt effectual means to poliſh the one and reform the other, Founded this Seminary (whoſe Secular Solemnity we now Celebrate) whence true Religion, and Virtue, ſound Learning and ingenious Education, might always ſpring up and iſſue forth to Plant and Cultivate the reſt of the Land; She <hi>pour'd this Box of Pretious Ointment upon the Head</hi> or Capital of our Kingdom, whence it might ſtream or deſcend to the moſt diſtant parts, and refreſh the whole with its excellent <hi>ſavour;</hi> She laid in here ſuch laſting Supplies of Piety and Litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which, like <hi>Ointment,</hi> might ſmooth the natural roughneſs of our Temper, ſupple our moroſeſt Paſſions, make us of a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Countenance, render us active &amp; fit for any Employment to which Church or State ſhould call us; and, like a <hi>Sweet and Pretious Ointment</hi> too, might not only gratifie our own Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, improve and better our own Souls, but by a happy ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhed its agreeable influence on all that approach us; and thô ſome ignorant or envious by-ſtanders may (as <hi>Judas) with indignation ſay, to what purpoſe was this waſt?</hi> what need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Royal Munificence? yet we and all who are benefitted by this Auſpicious Foundation, muſt ever gratefully join with our Bleſſed Saviour in my Text, <hi>Verily</hi> we <hi>ſay unto you, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Goſpel</hi> (whoſe Holy Doctrine we have here ſuck'd in, and to the underſtanding and declaring of which we have been here train'd up and educated) <hi>ſhall be preach'd</hi> by any of us <hi>in the whole world, there alſo this, that this Woman has done</hi> for us, <hi>ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e told as a memorial of her.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103235:6"/>
            <p> Gratitude and ſenſe of Obligation are a kind of Civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which oblige us as Men to perform many excellent <note place="margin">Of Gratitude in general.</note> things, thô there were no Religion in the World to enforce 'em; He who preaches this Virtue, pleads the cauſe both of God and Man, ſince without it we can neither be Sociable nor Religious; for Thanks and Acknowledgments are a Tribute payable by the pooreſt, the moſt indigent wretch, the moſt forlorn Widow has ſtill her two Mites to throw in, has a Heart to be ſenſible of, and a Tongue to expreſs its ſence of a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit receiv'd; for ſurely Nature gives no Man a Mouth to be always Eating, and never ſaying Grace; nor a Hand only to graſp and to receive: but as 'tis furniſh'd with Teeth for the one, ſo it ſhould likewiſe have a Tongue for the other; and the Hands which are ſo often reach'd out to take and to accept, ſhould ſometimes too be lifted up to bleſs. The beautiful ſyſteme of Providence, the whole courſe of Nature is one great argument for Gratitude; and the World only a larger <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>change,</hi> in which one benefit is, or ought to be, the ſtated price of another. If we conſider the Univerſe as one Great Body Politick, we may ſuppoſe Commerce, Society, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation to ſupply the office of the Blood and Spirits, and 'tis Gratitude that makes 'em circulate; this is the great Spring that ſets all the Wheels of Nature a going, the Band or Cement that holds together the differing, and otherwiſe inconſiſtent parts of the Creation: one may evidently diſcover it in all the Elements, in the Air and Flame, in the Seas and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, in the Earth and Sun, in the friendly correſpondence between the higher and the lower World; ſo that the Monſtrous Man who has a Soul wholly void of Gratitude, would do well to ſet his Soul to learn of any of theſe, nay even of his own Body, for all the parts of that do kindly and mutually ſerve each other; the Hands and Limbs labour dayly to bring in Food and Proviſion to the Stomach, (as it is hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly applied in <hi>Menenius Agrippa</hi>'s Apologue) which is grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully return'd in ſtrength and nutriment, diffuſed to all the members of the Body. And is not then the Ungrateful Man a reproach to the Creation, a manifeſt exception from all the viſible World? neither the Heavens above, nor the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103235:7"/> afford any thing like him, there is nothing beſides him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf but Hell, which is both the Region and the Emblem of Ingratitude, that is always receiving and never endeavouring to require; Ingratitude is inſtead of all other Vices in the ballance of Morality, a counterpoiſe to them all; 'tis one great blot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Humanity, and gives completion to the black Roll of nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous other ſins.</p>
            <p>Now if even Natural Religion prompts ſo ſtrongly to this Duty, what impreſſions muſt the Goſpel make, which ſo far outſhines both the dim Light of that, and the brighter Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Law? which has ſo far refined upon all the Duties of Morality, that it declares even Anger and Harſh Words to be Murder, and looks and deſires Adultery, that one may ſtab with his Tongue, aſſaſſinate with his Mind, and pollute him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a glance; which obliges us to love, bleſs, and do good to our moſt implacable Enemies; then what tender ſentiments, what a rapturous ſenſe of real Love muſt it inſpire for Friends <note place="margin">Of the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude due to our Founders and Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors.</note> and Benefactors? who have here expreſs'd the nobleſt Charity to us, and confer'd the moſt important and laſting Obligations upon us, by cloathing our moſt ſhameful Nakedneſs, our Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, our Errors, our Prejudices; by feeding our hungry Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, by furniſhing our Minds; by healing our perverſe Inclinations; and placing us in the path way to Heaven; theſe are <hi>truly</hi> Obligations as eternal as our Souls, and therefore 'tis but reaſonable that our Gratitude, the memory of them ſhou'd be as immortal alſo.</p>
            <p>But Words and Complements are no ſutable return to our Pious Benefactors, our juſteſt Acknowledgments muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd by a diligent endeavouring to anſwer all the great and uſeful ends of their Donations, by promoting the knowledge and practiſe of Religion and Piety, the advancement of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by a ſedulous application to all the improvements of Education, and a careful managing the tender ſprings of Youth.</p>
            <p>Now to ſhew how neceſſary the Inſtitution of Univerſities <note place="margin">The mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold uſefulneſs of Univerſities and Colleges.</note> and Colleges is to the attainment of all theſe great deſigns, as alſo the numerous advantages which the Learning and Arts therein cultivated derive to all the degrees and ſtations of life,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103235:7"/> as it will beſt inſtruct us in our Duty, ſo it may in ſome meaſure contribute to perpetuate the Memory of our Munificent Founders and Benefactors, oncourage others to imitate their Generous Examples, and be a Subject moſt proper and ſutable to this preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>But here it may be expedient to remove a miſchievous preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice <note place="margin">An Object<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt Aca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mick ſtudies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwer'd.</note> againſt Academick Studies, which comes recommended in a venerable impoſing Proverbial Dreſs, as if <hi>Ignorance</hi> were the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly True Mother of <hi>Devotion,</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> of <hi>Atheiſm;</hi> however antient this ſaying may be, 'tis certain that Humane Nature and the Service of God are little beholden to them who firſt intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the falſe obſervation, as if Simplicity and Dulneſs were becoming Qualifications for the Divine Worſhip, or that the Light of Reaſon ſhould ever be likely to produce a Spiritual Darkneſs; The Jewiſh Law forbad to Offer a Sacrifice to God that had a Blemiſh, yet this Opinion, while it beſtows the moſt Excellent and Uſeful of all the Race of Mankind on the Devil, aſſigns to Religion only thoſe Men, and thoſe Times, which are ſtigmatiz'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with the greateſt blemiſh of Humane Nature, namely, a Defect of Knowledge and Underſtanding: nay, as if God had deſpiſed our Rational Services, it complements him ſtill with Brutiſh Sacrifices, <hi>Man without <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> being juſtly compared (by the <hi>Pſalmiſt)</hi> to <hi>the Beaſts that periſh;</hi> both Reaſon and Revelation aſſure us, that all Sin and Error proceed from Ignorance, that 'tis the blindneſs of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding which miſguides the Will, and our Bleſſed Saviour ſays the ſame thing to the Jews, <hi>Ye do err</hi> (ſays he) <hi>not knowing the Scriptures and the Power of God,</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> which Reveal his <hi>Will,</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> his <hi>Power;</hi> as if the ſtudy of theſe two Books were the beſt preſervative from Error and Irreligion, and ſo it has always proved; to omit the former (which yet makes one of the nobleſt parts of that Knowledg and Learn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">The Uſef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs of Huma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Learning to ſacred Know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge and Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> I am diſcourſing of) how muſt the contemplation of the Admirable Order and oeconomy of Nature in all its Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Periods, in all its ſeveral Seaſons and Revolutions: how muſt the ſtudy of the ſurprizing reſults of a Regular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that Harmonious Concordance which runs through all the parts of the Univerſe, and renders them mutually ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103235:8"/> to each other, not only charm our Thoughts with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Idaeas, but likewiſe inſenſibly raiſe 'em up to the great Author and Contriver of this wonderful Maſterpiece? When God himſelf would repreſent his own Magnificence and Glory, he directs to his Works; he bids <hi>Job</hi> conſider his Earth, his Ocean, his Clouds and Rain, that is, he bids him be a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher; and Holy Men in Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure, when they wou'd quicken their own Souls and thoſe of others to Praiſe him; ſend their Thoughts abroad among the Creatures, to the ſtupendious Furniture of Land, Air, and Seas, to gather inſtances of Ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knowledgment: By the help of this Proſpect we may diſcover conſpicuous Characters of Gods Omnipotence, and ſound his Wiſdom as far as the ſhort line of Humane Reaſon is capable; thus by the Scale of Viſibles, Contemplation and Knowledge lead us up to that Supreme Inviſible Power which gives the Spring and Motion to all this mighty Machine; and by the ſteps and links of the Creation, our Inquiſitions may guide us till we aſcend to the top of that Chain, which the Poets feign'd was faſtned to <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Throne.</p>
            <p>Such dawnings of Divinity does each part of Knowledge contain, that the Aſtronomer finds a Deity in the Uniform Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Coeleſtial Bodies, and Regular Viciſſitude of Seaſons; The Phyloſopher in the delightful variety of Natural Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, their Beauty, Order, and conſpiring tendency to the great ends of the Creation; The Hiſtorian in the wonderful turns of Providence, and manifeſt Diſcoveries of the Divine Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Revolutions of the World: and thô the Obvious Firmament, the Viſible Beauties of the great World, and the appearing variety and fitneſs of thoſe parts which make up the little one in Man, could ſcarce ſecure <hi>Galen</hi> from Atheiſm: Yet when he pried farther by Anatomical Inquiries, and ſaw the ſurprizing diverſity, aptneſs, and order of the minuteſt Fibres and Paſſages that are in the inward Fabrick, he could not then abſtain from the devoutneſs of an Anthem of Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment; nor can it otherwiſe happen, but that the Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which are dayly made by Study in God's Immenſe Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, muſt needs every moment fill the Soul with pleaſant aſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment, and enflame the Heart with the ardors of the higheſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103235:8"/> Love and Devotion, and the Contemplation of God's Works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> join'd with theſe natural pious Sentiments, ſeem almoſt an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of that Bright and Clear Knowledg, which we ſhall hereafter enjoy in Heaven. Nay, of ſuch a pious tendency is Learning, that in proportion to the Phyloſophy, and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, in which various Nations excell'd, God has generally been worſhipped in former Ages; Thus in <hi>Perſia</hi> and <hi>Chaldaea,</hi> where the Skill of Heavenly Motions firſt began, they had their Temples on the Tops of Hills, and Open to the Air: In <hi>Egypt,</hi> where they had the beſt opportunities of ſtudying the Natures of Living Creatures, by reaſon of that Variety, which their River and Land produced; all their Religious Myſteries were contain'd in Hieroglyphicks, borrow'd from Beaſts and Animals: And ſhall Learning now be ſtigmatiz'd for contempt of Divinity, when of old it did rather incline Men to Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is the ſuperſaetation and rankneſs of Religion, and quite the other extreme? Formerly Prieſts and Scholars were Synonimous Words, and the great Apoſtles of Natural Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, the Preachers of Un-enlightened Divinity thrô the World, were no others than the Phyloſophers and Wiſemen; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Nature, being nothing elſe but the Inſtrument of God, whereby he gives Being and Action to things, the knowledge of that, and other Uſeful Science, ſhould be ſo far from being accounted Dangerous or Impious, that it ought rather to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd a ſubordinate Theology, a neceſſary ſtep and gradation to thoſe exalted Myſterious Truths, which revealed Religion diſcovers to us. And agreeably hereunto we find the Patriarchs and Holy Men of antient times, that were moſt in God's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, were alſo beſt Inſtructed in the Knowledge of his Works, and Contributed moſt to the good of Mankind by their Uſeful Diſcoveries and Inventions: <hi>Adam</hi> (we read) was acquainted with the Natures of all Living Creatures; <hi>Noah,</hi> a Planter of Vineyards; <hi>Abraham</hi> (as <hi>Grotius</hi> collects) an Excellent Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomer; <hi>Iſaac,</hi> proſperous in Agriculture; <hi>Jacob,</hi> bleſſed in his Phyloſophical Experiment and Stratagem of the Speckled Rods; <hi>Moſes,</hi> eminent in all the Wiſdom of the <hi>Egyptians; Bazaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab,</hi> inſpired in Architecture; <hi>Solomon,</hi> a deep Naturaliſt; <hi>Daniel,</hi> and his Brethren, skill'd in all Learning and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103235:9"/> Wiſdom, and (not to multiply Inſtances) they were the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> the <hi>Magi</hi> or <hi>Wiſemen,</hi> who expreſſed the moſt Early Piety and Zeal for Chriſtianity, and made firſt Addreſſes to the Infant Saviour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, who was the moſt Refined Politick E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy that ever Chriſtianity had, well knew how beneficial ſound Learning ever was to true Religion, and therefore the Edict which he publiſhed to ſuppreſs all Chriſtian Schools and Colleges, was juſtly eſteem'd a more pernitious Engine to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw our Religion, than all the moſt Bloody Perſecutions of former Emperors.</p>
            <p>Let them therefore, whoſe Intereſt it is to preach up <hi>ſaving Ignorance, implicit Faith,</hi> and <hi>blind Credulity;</hi> who cou'd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Aſſertion of <hi>Antipodes</hi> to be a point of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and impriſon poor <hi>Galileo</hi> in the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> for proving the <hi>Earth's Motion;</hi> who cou'd pronounce <hi>Mathematicks</hi> heretofore to be <hi>Magick,</hi> and find <hi>Damnable Hereſie</hi> in <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew:</hi> Let ſuch (I ſay) applaud Ignorance as the Mother of Devotion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all curious Reſearches and free Diſquiſitions in Learning, and write Encomiums upon paſſive credulous Simplicity; 'tis certain our Church and Religion can never be ſafer than amidſt the Conſequences of a Rational Learned Age, and all the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Improvements of Knowledge, ſince they aim not at the Captivity but Freedom of Men's Minds; and we can never make War againſt Learning, without Undermining one of our chief Strengths, our moſt ſucceſsful Weapon, with which we combat Enthuſiaſm on one hand, and Superſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ition on the other.</p>
            <p>And thus having not only vindicated Human Learning, and the Arts that are here cultivated; from an unjuſt Prejudice; but likewiſe ſhewn their great Uſefulneſs and Subſerviency to all ſacred Knowledge &amp; Religion: The Proofs will lie more eaſie and obvious, how they <hi>farther</hi> tend to the Improvement &amp; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our Minds; and are the fruitful Parents of all thoſe profitable Diſcoveries which render the <hi>Life</hi> of Man <hi>Happy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Human Learning to Government, and all the In- <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and <hi>Comfortable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Poets with great Significancy feign'd <hi>Minerva</hi> as well to be the Goddeſs of Arms, as Patroneſs of Arts, intimating
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103235:9"/> doubtleſs, That Empire did ever beſt flouriſh and grow up in Conjunction with Learning; witneſs the Antient Principalities of <hi>Greece,</hi> thoſe Celebrated Schools at once of War and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, where their greateſt Generals were taken out of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, from under the Inſtitution of Wiſe Men and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, from the Calm and Retirement of a Study; where <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> cou'd furniſh out a Pupil <hi>Xenophon,</hi> raw and undiſciplin'd, to perform one of the greateſt Actions of Antiquity; and a ſingle <hi>Archimedes</hi> with his Rule and Compaſs could defend <hi>Syra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe,</hi> and defie for a long time the whole Force of <hi>Marcellus</hi>'s Army: Witneſs <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, whoſe Empire was never in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Glory than when Arts too and Ingenuity were moſt cultivated and encouraged, <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> from an Orator became a Hero, and is ſtill perhaps as juſtly Celebrated for his Commentaries as his Conqueſts. <hi>Scipio</hi> the Great is reported to have ſpent more time in his Study then in his Camp, and was oftner ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved with a Book than a Sword in his Hand; nay Learning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them was the undoubted and infallible ſtep to all ſorts of Preferment; it Recommended their Conſuls and their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, nor could the Government of Nations, the Diſpatch of Armies, the Noiſe of Victories interrupt their Studies: They writ Books even with Triumphal Hands, and Argued and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted with Phyloſophers, thô they had Legions at command. From the days of <hi>Nerva</hi> down to <hi>Commodus</hi> was the Happieſt Age the Roman Empire ever knew, whether we conſider its vaſt Extent, or the great Felicity and Peace in which it was Govern'd; and then we find none but <hi>Plato</hi>'s wiſh'd for Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, ſuch as were Phyloſophers too, a ſucceſſion of <hi>Antonines, Trajans, Adrians,</hi> ſuch Wiſe and Learned Princes, as brought Knowledge into Faſhion and Repute; gain'd it admiſſion into Courts and Palaces; taught it to keep the Beſt Company; render'd it the ſtudy of States-men and Politicians; the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of the Rich and of the Great. But not to wander ſo far; who among the <hi>Saxons</hi> was a greater encourager of Learning then King <hi>Alfred?</hi> and who too, more Victorious in his Arms, and more Wiſe and Regular in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Affairs? And to come yet nearer to our preſent Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; When were theſe Nations more Happy, then under the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103235:10"/> long and glorious Reign of our Illuſtrious <hi>Foundreſs?</hi> whom as we muſt always gratefully own to be the <hi>Beſt Patroneſs</hi> of Arts and Knowledge, the Reſtorer of Decay'd Learning among us. ſo all the World will grant Her not only to have been the <hi>Moſt Learned</hi> of Her <hi>Sex,</hi> but to have exceeded in this Particular, as well as in Wiſdom and other Princely Vertues, all the Contemporary Monarchs and Princes in Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>To deſcend yet lower; 'T would be almoſt infinite to reckon up the various Helps and Compendiums which Learning has furniſhed to all the Inferior Arts, to the Entertainments of Peace, as well as the Succeſſes of War. What Improvements do Trade, Commerce, Navigation, the Culture of Lands and the Advancement of Mechanicks in general owe thereto? nay if we will not give theſe uſeful Inventions an <hi>Epicurean</hi> original, and impute 'em wholly to <hi>Blind Chance</hi> or a <hi>fortuitous</hi> concourſe of <hi>Lucky Thoughts,</hi> we muſt believe they proceeded from an unwearied vigorous inveſtigation of <hi>Nature</hi> and it's Powers, from a ſedulous tracing ſuch Links and Connexions, Corolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Conſequences, as none but a Thinking Learned Head is acquainted with.</p>
            <p>In ſumm, <hi>Antiquity</hi> owes all it's <hi>Heathen Gods</hi> and Divinities to the fruitful Induſtry of <hi>Scholars,</hi> the Admiring World of old <hi>deified</hi> their Diſcoveries, Built Temples and Raiſed Altars to the happy products of <hi>Science;</hi> and thô <hi>Theſeus, Minos,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus,</hi> who were Founders of Empires and Fathers of their Country, cou'd only arrive to the Inferior Honour of <hi>Heroes</hi> and <hi>Demigods:</hi> yet <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Bacchus, Mercury</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> who invented <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> and obliged the World with more laſting and advantageous Benefits, were Worſhip'd with the <hi>higheſt</hi> degree of Adoration and ranked among the <hi>Dij majorum Gentium.</hi> And doubtleſs the Diſcoveries of the latter bringing perpetual Profit and Advantage with them, being <hi>gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> and <hi>eaſy; like the ſtill ſmall voice,</hi> had more evident Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of a Divine Preſence and Efficacy then all the boiſterous noiſie tranſient Benefits of the former.</p>
            <p>But if any are more affected with the pleaſures of <hi>Thinking</hi> and <hi>Meditation</hi> (which indeed is properly to act as Men) no other Employment can afford the like Advantages. All other
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103235:10"/> Delights are mixt and <hi>adulterate</hi> and do chiefly gratify our <hi>Bodies</hi> or <hi>Senſitive</hi> parts; are acquired with <hi>Expence</hi> and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard,</hi> and do either <hi>weaken</hi> Nature, or <hi>nauſeate</hi> in the very enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: whereas theſe render the conſtitution of the Mind more <hi>vigorous</hi> and <hi>healthy,</hi> it's Faculties are made more <hi>bright</hi> and <hi>active</hi> by conſtant uſe, their fruition does not <hi>exclude Appetite,</hi> while we drink we thirſt, and by a grateful viciſſitude of <hi>Deſiring</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſſing,</hi> are always in Action and always Happy, And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed what more manly and becoming, as well as Noble Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment can there be, than to improve our beſt Talents, and enlarge and extend our Spirits? while we induſtriouſly <hi>culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> our Lands, and <hi>adorn</hi> our Bodies, is it fit our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> ſhould ly <hi>fallow</hi> &amp; <hi>barren,</hi> and the Divine Image which we carry within us remain <hi>neglected, diſhonored,</hi> and unimproved? Is it fit our <hi>Mindes,</hi> which are large enough to embrace the <hi>whole World,</hi> and comprehend the vaſteſt <hi>Truths,</hi> ſhou'd be buſied only Servilely to cater for the Body, and not rather employ themſelves according to the <hi>dignity</hi> of their <hi>exalted</hi> Natures, and be cultivated and adorned as becomes their <hi>Heavenly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction?</hi> 'Tis the perfection of our Rational Part to <hi>know,</hi> that is, to be able to frame <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>diſtinct</hi> Conceptions, to form <hi>right</hi> Judgments, and to draw <hi>true</hi> Conſequences from one thing to another; and Reaſon is the undoubted <hi>Birthright</hi> and <hi>Patrimony</hi> of every man, and whoever will ſuffer this valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Entail'd Eſtate to ly <hi>waſt</hi> and <hi>uſeleſs,</hi> or be <hi>Mortgag'd</hi> and <hi>Squander'd</hi> away for Trifles, does ſcarce merit Pitty, if he become Poor, Deſpiſed, and Miſerable.</p>
            <p>But to be more ſucceſsful yet in the behalf of Learning, we will bribe the <hi>Senſual</hi> Appetites and <hi>Affections</hi> of Men, and ſhew that even their <hi>Luſts</hi> and <hi>Paſſions</hi> may find repoſe there. Is any one ambitious of <hi>Fame</hi> and <hi>Glory?</hi> 'Tis this ſhews the readieſt path thereto, and will furniſh out a <hi>Name, pretious</hi> as the Benefits it derives on Mankind, and <hi>laſting</hi> as the Books and Monuments in which they are Regiſtred. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s <hi>Works</hi> will be known, read, and admired, when his great <hi>Patron</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts may perhaps be forgotten; and the Reputation of <hi>Achilles</hi> is much more obliged for it's duration to <hi>Homer</hi>'s <hi>Pen,</hi> than his own <hi>Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:103235:11"/>
            <p> Is any fond of <hi>Empire</hi> and <hi>Command? Learning</hi> eſtabliſhes the moſt diffuſive <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy,</hi> extending its Power to the moſt diſtant Nations, and making a Conqueſt over all that is <hi>rational;</hi> Tyrants may <hi>enſlave</hi> the <hi>Body,</hi> and by Rigor and Injuſtice preſerve an uneaſie tottering Command; but the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> of <hi>Knowledge</hi> is over the <hi>Will</hi> and the <hi>Mind,</hi> it fixes its Throne in the <hi>Souls</hi> of Men, and rules their <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are we deſirous to Keep the <hi>Beſt Company,</hi> and Converſe familiarly with the <hi>Moſt Ingenious,</hi> the Greateſt and Wiſeſt Men that ever were? In Books we may <hi>freely talk</hi> with the moſt Celebrated <hi>Phyloſophers,</hi> and com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endiouſly reap the advantage of all their Studies and Improvements; there we ſhall find <hi>Reaſon</hi> without <hi>Paſſion, Learning</hi> without <hi>Affectation,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Eloquence</hi> without <hi>Noiſe</hi> or <hi>Clamor;</hi> by their means we may Converſe with <hi>Mighty Heroes,</hi> whom in their Lifetime we durſt ſcarce perhaps Salute with our Eyes; We may be admitted <hi>Confidents</hi> to Statesmen, hear <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> haranguing in open Senate, be preſent while <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> ſpeak to their Armies, ſee them Riding in their <hi>Triumphal</hi> Chariots, and Receiving the Acclamations and Applauſes of the People. And all theſe Privileges we may arrive too, without <hi>Attendance</hi> and <hi>Crowding,</hi> without <hi>Brihing</hi> or <hi>Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> without <hi>Sawcineſs</hi> or <hi>Intruſion.</hi> Thus by the aſſiſtance of Books and Learning we may acquire a kind of <hi>Intellectual Omnipreſence</hi> in <hi>all Ages,</hi> and to <hi>all Places;</hi> 'tis thus we break into <hi>all</hi> the <hi>hidden receſſes</hi> of <hi>Truth;</hi> Indefatigable Reading brings in a vaſt ſtock of matter, which is often without <hi>form</hi> and <hi>void,</hi> like the firſt <hi>Chaos,</hi> till <hi>Thinking</hi> and <hi>Contemplation,</hi> like the <hi>ſeminal Spirit, agitate</hi> the <hi>dull ſhapeleſs lump,</hi> and work it up into <hi>Figure</hi> and <hi>Symetry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, What <hi>Raptures</hi> can the <hi>Voluptuous</hi> Man fancy, to which thoſe of <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> are not equal? If he can reliſh nothing but the pleaſure of his <hi>Senſes, Natural Phyloſophy</hi> expoſes the <hi>beautiful boſome</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> to his view, admits him into <hi>Nature</hi>'s Garden, where he may taſte of its Fruits, and ſatisfie himſelf with its Plenty; learn, not only to admire, but, comprehend all its <hi>ſurpriſing Phoenomena. Mathematicks</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:103235:11"/> diſcover all the <hi>delightful</hi> Contrivances of <hi>Art,</hi> unfold all it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>curious Springs</hi> and <hi>latent Cauſes,</hi> and inſtruct the Buſie Mind how to improve and better former Inventions; from moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious <hi>Principles,</hi> by a <hi>natural progreſs</hi> and aſcent, the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> riſes to the <hi>boldeſt</hi> Truths, tracing the Chain of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions</hi> from Link to Link, and ſtill difluſing it ſelf over <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> Regions of new <hi>Diſcoveries,</hi> wherein no <hi>fallacious</hi> Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of <hi>veriſimilitude</hi> intervene, there is no <hi>ſuſpition</hi> of any latent <hi>miſtake,</hi> turn the <hi>Theorem</hi> which way you pleaſe, in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry light the Mind is ſtill in <hi>full aquieſcence,</hi> in moſt ſecure <hi>poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion</hi> of it's Valuable Purchaſe; moſt other <hi>Knowledge</hi> (how diverting ſoever) is yet ſtill <hi>conjectural</hi> and <hi>litigious,</hi> whereas <hi>Peripatetick</hi> and <hi>Carteſian, Catholick</hi> and <hi>Heretick,</hi> do all agree in a <hi>Mathematical demonſtration,</hi> which is yet a farther convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>great Excellency</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> of its <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Twould be <hi>endleſs</hi> to run th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ô all, to deſcribe the great and uſeful Images which <hi>Hiſtory</hi> furniſhes, the Subtilty of <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Metaphiſick,</hi> the Advantages of <hi>Moral Philoſophy,</hi> the reſiſtleſs Power of <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> and the Charms of <hi>Poetry;</hi> it is ſufficient to have pointed out ſuch <hi>general</hi> Inſtances, whence it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that all the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> as well as the <hi>Ornaments</hi> and Comforts of Life, are derived from the <hi>retired Thinking</hi> Man.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, no one <hi>Humor</hi> has furniſhed the <hi>Stage</hi> with more pleaſant <hi>Scenes,</hi> or afforded a larger Harveſt to <hi>Comedy</hi> and <hi>Burleſque</hi> then the Actions, Geſtures, Habits, and Expreſſions-of <hi>Scholars; Ariſtophanes</hi> of old diverted the <hi>Athenians</hi> by Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculing <hi>Socrates,</hi> and the fruitful <hi>Satyr</hi> has been plentifully propagated to our times; coming out of the <hi>retired</hi> ſilence of a <hi>Colledge</hi> and Study, they are ſuppoſed to be deafned by the <hi>noiſe,</hi> or <hi>dazled</hi> with the <hi>falſe Glories</hi> of the <hi>World;</hi> their <hi>Seden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> Life is thought to unfit 'em for Activity and all Buſineſs, to render 'em <hi>ſheepiſh</hi> in their Looks, <hi>flegmatick</hi> in their Tempers, <hi>mopiſh</hi> in their Converſations, <hi>ridiculous</hi> in their Behaviour, and expoſed to a thouſand pleaſant <hi>Abſurdities,</hi> which a man of the <hi>World</hi> wou'd eſcape; but 'tis to be fear'd that they who obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct at this diverting rate, miſtake <hi>Affectation</hi> and <hi>Pedantry</hi> for <hi>Learning,</hi> the <hi>Sordid Ape</hi> for the <hi>Man; true</hi> Learning takes in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103235:12"/> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>theory</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> as well as <hi>Nature,</hi> and it's Object is as <hi>large</hi> and <hi>univerſal</hi> as the very Notion of <hi>Being;</hi> it Reads the <hi>World</hi> as much as <hi>Books,</hi> Recommends <hi>Converſation</hi> as well as <hi>Study,</hi> and joyns <hi>Experience</hi> and <hi>Contemplation</hi> together to perfect and compleat the Mind.</p>
            <p>But to come cloſer yet to the Occaſion of our preſent Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; As Water (to uſe the Excellent Lord <hi>Bacon</hi>'s compariſon) whether it <hi>deſcend</hi> in Dew from Heaven, or <hi>ſpring</hi> out of Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the earth, is eaſily <hi>loſt,</hi> unleſs it be <hi>preſerved</hi> in certain <hi>receptacles,</hi> where by <hi>union</hi> and <hi>collection</hi> it may be kept and increaſed, whence humane induſtry has deſign'd <hi>Aquoeducts, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns,</hi> and <hi>Ponds,</hi> adorn'd as well for <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Magnificence,</hi> as contrived for <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>neceſſity:</hi> So likewiſe this <hi>precious liquor</hi> of <hi>knowledge</hi> (this ſacred <hi>ointment</hi> of my text) whether it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd by <hi>divine inſpiration,</hi> or <hi>convey'd</hi> from our <hi>ſenſes,</hi> wou'd ſoon <hi>periſh</hi> and be <hi>loſt,</hi> were it not preſerved in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, Colledges,</hi> and <hi>Schools,</hi> which are the laſting <hi>Fountains</hi> and <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitories</hi> of Learning, whence with glad ſtreams it flows to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh</hi> and make ſertile all the neighbouring land. A <hi>ſolitary</hi> unaſſiſted induſtry, tho never ſo <hi>indefatigable;</hi> is rarely known to produce any thing <hi>great</hi> or <hi>extraordinary;</hi> whereas no part of knowledge ſeems inſuperable to the <hi>joint</hi> endeavors of a well regulated Society, <hi>united</hi> in common ſtudies and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of the ſame uſeful ends; in the former 'tis like ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of a <hi>private</hi> Eſtate; in the latter, as out of a <hi>publick</hi> Fund, or Treaſury; Add to this, the new lights which are daily ſtruck out, and appear by <hi>mutual Converſe,</hi> the happy effects of a <hi>generous Emulation</hi> (which is the moſt impetuous powerful Spring to all the good performances of Youth) and above all, the ineſtimable advantages of <hi>Education,</hi> and forming the <hi>Minds</hi> and <hi>Manners</hi> of the tender waxen Age, by laying the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a holy and happy life, and adding ſeveral cubits to the ſtature of our minds; which render ſuch Societies as this, the beſt ſecurity of Vertue and Piety, the bulwarks of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the moſt publick Bleſsings of a Nation,</p>
            <p>'Twas truly obſerved by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that we are at firſt born <hi>meer Animals,</hi> to be afterwards Educated and brought up into <hi>men;</hi> our <hi>Reaſon</hi> then ſeems (in a great meaſure) to be the birth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103235:12"/> of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Inſtitution;</hi> and the Mind of man is ſuch a <hi>Jewel,</hi> that tho it bring its perfections from the Bed, yet they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together <hi>rough</hi> and <hi>unpoliſhed;</hi> much pains and art are required to <hi>faſhion</hi> their rudeneſs, to conceal the flaws, and as well to <hi>form</hi> as <hi>cultivate</hi> the tender Seeds; and in the care of this, the <hi>Chineſes</hi> (if we may truſt the relations made of them) do juſtly boaſt they have out done all other Nations, having erected the moſt noble Edifices for the <hi>inſtruction</hi> of <hi>Youth,</hi> alotted the moſt <hi>liberal maintenance</hi> to the Profeſſors and Teachers, and thought no Honours and Reſpects too great to be given them, who lay out their whole time and powers on the <hi>Improvement</hi> of others; rich perſons are often expenſive upon trifles, about the mere circumſtances of life, and uſeleſs ornaments of a man; they can often afford to be <hi>generous</hi> to thoſe who <hi>inſtruct</hi> the <hi>feet</hi> and the <hi>hands;</hi> and is it fit then, that they who labour to <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> the <hi>head</hi> with uſeful Knowledge, to <hi>adorn</hi> the <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Soul,</hi> and to enable men to ſerve their God <hi>piouſly,</hi> and their Countrey <hi>uſefully:</hi> Is it not a reproach (I ſay) that <hi>ſuch</hi> alone ſhou'd be ſacrificed to <hi>Thrift,</hi> or <hi>ſordid Avarice?</hi> Life is a <hi>Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> not an anxious <hi>Pilgrimage;</hi> and doubtleſs therefore, the <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> of the World ſhou'd be the rather afforded to <hi>us;</hi> and competent <hi>Riches</hi> and <hi>Honours</hi> allowed to our Baiting pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whoſe whole buſineſs it is to <hi>ſtudy</hi> the <hi>Improvement</hi> of others, to <hi>manage</hi> the <hi>unequal temper</hi> of <hi>Youth,</hi> and to <hi>Cultivate</hi> growing Vertue and Learning.</p>
            <p>This our Munificent <hi>Founders</hi> and <hi>Benefactors</hi> well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; and therefore thought they cou'd not employ their Wealth more <hi>advantageouſly,</hi> or place it in a <hi>ſecurer</hi> Treaſury, than by <hi>ſuch</hi> pious Erections, where <hi>True Religion</hi> might be taught, <hi>Vertue</hi> Inculcated, <hi>Learning</hi> Improved, and a conſtant ſupply of uſeful men both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> furniſhed out and prepared. What the Poor are ordinarily relieved with, is not ſo much the Giver's Alms, as their exigence; and, as neceſsity requires it, ſo it quickly periſhes: But theſe liberal Oblations, as they ſavour of a more <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>deeper</hi> Charity, are too of a more <hi>laſting</hi> ſubſiſtance, beſides the <hi>Eternal</hi> Treaſures which are laid up for the <hi>Donors,</hi> they provide for the <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity</hi> and propagation of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> to all ſuccced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103235:13"/> Ages, and may truly be ſaid to <hi>Honour God,</hi> and be <hi>uſeful</hi> to their <hi>Countrey,</hi> not only in <hi>themſelves,</hi> but in <hi>all</hi> that by ſuch their Bounty are maintained and educated. This is properly to <hi>Convert</hi> and Proſelyte <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmon,</hi> to <hi>Conſecrate</hi> that as an <hi>Offering,</hi> which was before an <hi>Idol:</hi> this is to make this Earth <hi>tributary</hi> to Heaven; and in a much <hi>nobler</hi> ſenſe than the new Syſtem of <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> teaches, advance it into a <hi>Star,</hi> a <hi>Coeleſtial Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That their <hi>Memories</hi> therefore and <hi>Benefits</hi> may be <hi>ever gratefully</hi> Celebrated, and their Names remain pretious, and ſacred among us; that their <hi>generous Examples</hi> may excite other well diſpoſed Perſons and Benefactors to an <hi>imitation,</hi> and that we may always anſwer the <hi>great</hi> and <hi>uſeful</hi> ends of our <hi>Foundation,</hi> ſhall be our conſtant <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Endeavour.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Praiſe the Lord therefore with Me, ye Servants of the Lord, ye that dwell in the Courts of the Houſe of our God, and let us magnifie his Name together.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
